斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到 2013/14 学年秋季 CS193P 课程第三讲
Okay, well welcome to Lecture number 3 of CS193p for fall of 2013/14.
今天我将直接跳到一个 demo
Today I’m going to jump right into a demo and then
然后我有一些幻灯片
after that I have some slides, time permitting,
假设 demo 不需要整堂课时间
assuming the demo doesn’t take the whole time here,
demo 要做的是
and after, the demo I’m going to do is I’m going
将上周我们做的纸牌工作用到真正的纸牌匹配游戏
to take the little card thing we did last week and turn it into a real card matching game
我们将真正开始匹配 而不只是翻来翻去
where we’re actually matching cards, okay, rather than just flipping them over.
如果时间允许
And, like I say, if I have the time
我还会进一步讲 Objective-C
I’ll talk a little bit more about objective-C and we’re really going to go
周三我将非常详细地讲到 Objective-C
into objective-C on Wednesday in quite a bit of detail.
我还附上了一些复习幻灯片在最后
I also included on the stuff I posted some review slides at the end just kind
复习前三讲我们所学的内容
of reviewing what we will have learned in the first three lectures,
让你们能够快速回顾 并问自己是否理解
just so you can kind of look through it real quick and say oh yeah, do I know that?
Yeah I do,
如果不记得 你显然需要发帖向我们提问
and if not, then you can obviously post and ask us questions about it.
好 我们来做这个 demo
OK. So, let’s do this demo.
demo 是这样的
So for the demo,
实际上 在 demo 最开始
I’m going to start this demo actually
我将公布作业的答案
by giving you the solution to the homework,
我讲过我要做这个的 本学期只有一次我会这样做
I told you I was going to do this, this is the only time
that I’m going to do this this quarter.
一般我不会讲答案
Normally I don’t go over the solution,
但这里答案很简单 而且需要知道这些答案
but the solution’s so simple and because obviously we need the solution of this
我们才能继续今天后面的内容
to move on to what I’m going to do today.
所以先看答案
We’ll do the solution first.
这里我启动了 XCode
So here I’m just launching XCode, you can see now
最近文件中有上次编辑的 Machismo
in my recents I have this machismo from last time.
打开这个
So, we’ll bring that up.
好了 确保我们使用了
There it is. Make sure that we’re using
尽量多的屏幕空间
as much screen real estate as we can here.
把这些线挪开
Get these wires out of my way.
好 从上次结束的地方开始 你们做过作业 应该记得
Okay. So, from where we left off, hopefully you remember because you did your homework.
我们有这一张牌
We just have this single, this card, single card,
它在梅花 A 和反面间来回翻动
and it flips back and forth between the ace and the clubs,
你们的作业是在课上模型的基础上
and your homework was to use the model that we worked on in lecture
让它从整个牌堆中抽牌翻转
to make it flip through an entire deck.
这个答案非常简单
So, the solution to that is quite straightforward.
我们显然需要牌堆
We obviously need a deck so I’m just going
我将添加一个属性 强属性 必须是强的
to add a property here, strong property, should be strong
因为我们需要牌堆一直存在
because we need that deck to, to stay around, and it’s going
它是牌堆 取名 deck
to be a deck and I’m going to call it deck.
因为 deck 这里有个错误
Now we have an error here because of deck,
所以我们需要到上面这里 导入 Deck
so we have to go up here and import deck.
这样错误就没有了
Alright? To make that error go away.
现在我们有了这个属性 这很酷
So now we got this property that’s cool,
显然 我们希望使用惰性实例化来实例化这一属性
obviously we want to use lazy instantiation to instantiate that property,
所以我在这里输入 (Deck *)deck
so I’m going to do that, that’s a deck star deck,
我要看我的实例变量是否为 nil
and I’m just going to see if my instance variable is null
基本上也就是 是否为 0
or nil, rather, the 0, basically.
然后是_deck =
Then I’m going to say, sorry, underbar, underbar deck, equals,
我将使用另一个方法来创建 deck
and I’m actually going to create deck using another method here,
等下你们就知道为什么了 然后返回_deck
you’ll see why in a second and then I’m going to return underbar deck.
createDeck 将会创建一个牌堆
And create deck is just going to create a deck.
createDeck 我将创建一个扑克牌堆
Create deck and I’m going to create a playing card deck,
因为这就是我要求你们做的
because that’s what you were asked to do
这里用 alloc init 来做这个
so I’m just going to do alloc init to do that.
这里有个错误 因为只导入 Deck 是不行的
I got an error because not only do I need to import deck,
我们需要导入 PlayingCardDeck
but playing card deck, and it’s actually kind
很不幸的是 这里我要创建一个通用的纸牌游戏
of unfortunate here that in this nice, generic card game that I’m building,
结果却要导入扑克牌堆
that I’m importing a playing card deck.
为什么说这很不幸呢
Why is that unfortunate?
这里我要尝试创建一个纸牌游戏
Well, I’m going to try and build a card game here
它同扑克牌没有任何关系
that has nothing to do with playing cards.
它是通用的
It’s going to be a generic,
应该对任何牌堆都适用
should work with any kind of deck, okay, a deck of any kind
实际上 在你们的作业中
of cards and, in fact, in your homework, you’re going
你们下周会被要求考虑不同牌堆 来增强游戏
to be asked to enhanced the game next week to play a different deck.
所以说 这里需要这样做是很不幸的
So it’s unfortunate that I have to do this and in lecture,
在周三或周一 我将讨论如何把这个除掉
either on Wednesday or probably on Monday, we will talk about how we can get rid of this.
不再导入 PlayingCardDeck
Okay, get this import playing card deck
让这个 createDeck 方法更具通用性
and this create deck method to be more generic, okay,
而不仅仅适用于扑克牌
not be so specific to playing cards.
无论如何 这里我有了这个 deck
But anyway, so now I have this deck
它是惰性实例化的 有了 deck 后
and it’s lazily instantiated so now that I have a deck,
我就可以用它来替换这个梅花 A 了
I can use it to get rid of this little ace of clubs thing right here.
我可以这样做 这里加入 Card *card
And, I’m going to do that by saying here card star card
= [self.deck drawRandomCard]
equals self dot deck, draw random card.
我将从牌堆中随机抽取一张牌
So I’m going to draw a random card out of the deck
然后这里不再是梅花 A
and then instead of putting ace of clubs here,
将它改为纸牌内容
I’m going to put the cards contents.
这就是你们所有的作业内容
And that’s really your entire homework assignment,
这里我还要做两个小的改动
there’s one other minor thing that I’m going to do here, actually two minor things.
因为我们的答案不是能够工作就行
Because we don’t want just a solution that works,
运行这个确实能够工作
this will work if we run this.
能够工作 但并不优雅
We’re going to see it work, but it’s kind of not very elegant
这不能算一个很好的答案
and not really, it’s not really a really very good solution
虽然它能够达到目的
to the problem, even though it functions, you see, it’s,
可以看到 它会随机出牌
it’s going through the random cards here.
但有几点比较让人不爽
But it was kind of annoying, a couple of things.
一是它会从梅花 A 开始 这很毛糙
One, it started out with the ace of clubs, that was kind of gross,
因为一直点击这里
okay, because if I keep clicking here,
最终我会重新得到梅花 A 这就是了
eventually I’m going to get the ace of clubs, there it was, back again,
这很糟糕
so that’s kind of bad.
另一点是 当牌堆为空时
The other thing is when this deck is empty,
这个将没法善终
this is not going to particularly elegantly, you know, finish off,
我们需要优雅的答案
and we want to have some elegant solution and I said
提示中就涉及到过
in the hints come up with an elegant solution.
然后是翻转计数 纸牌用完后 它还会持续计数
Also, this flips thing here, once I flip through the whole deck, it’s going to keep flipping.
它会增加到 102 103 104 105 这不很优雅
You know, it’s going to be 102, 103, 104, 105, that’s not very elegant either.
让我们来修正上述三点 得到简单优雅的答案
So let’s fix all three of those things with simple, elegant solutions.
对于梅花 A 我的简单优雅答案
So my simple, elegant solution to the ace of clubs
是从反面开始 这个我其实提示过
which I hinted at for you is simply to start it face down.
我将用到 cardback 除掉梅花 A
So I’m going to get the card back here, get rid of the ace of clubs,
这时就是从反面开始了
and now this card starts out facedown.
我根本都不需要写任何代码
So I didn’t have to write any code and I just use my brain
直接在这里点几下就行了
over my brawn to make sure that this works, right?
这是解决那一问题的优雅方式
So, that’s kind of the elegant way of thinking about solving that problem.
我们将从正面朝下开始
So we’ll just start it face down, there
没有人要求一定要梅花 A 正面朝上
was no required task that said you had to start with the ace of clubs face up,
这是很好的解决办法
so that’s a good solution.
而对于纸牌用完的情况
When it comes to running out of cards,
我认为最优雅的解决办法是 这时就停止翻动
I think an elegant solution is it just will stop flipping at that point.
你当然也可以再加载一副牌
I mean, you could make arguments, load up another deck,
不过我认为最简单的解决办法是
other stuff, but I think a simple solution is just once you
牌用完时 再点就不翻了
run out of cards, you keep clicking, and it stops flipping.
这怎么做到呢
So how are we going to do that?
我知道你们有些人会说
Well, I know some of you are going to say something like,
如果翻转次数为 102 那么停止翻动
if number of flips equals 102, then stop flipping,
这非常糟糕
and that’s really, really bad.
这是非常糟糕的设计
That’s a very bad design,
因为 102 就像一个你加入到程序中的神奇数字
because that 102 is like a magic number you just put into your program
而且这种糟糕设计完全没有理由
and there’s completely no reason for that bad design either.
你只需要说 if (card)
All you need to do is just say if card,
那么翻转
then flip it,
这些表示翻转
okay, so I’m going to flip it here,
空出一点空间 这样更清楚一些
I’ll make some more space so you can see.
否则 牌就不会翻动
Otherwise, I’m not going to flip it.
这是超级优雅的解决办法
So I’m just, this is a super elegant solution to,
牌堆中牌用完时 这里就将不再翻动
you know, not continuing to flip this thing over when the deck runs out,
我们知道 drawRandomCard 会返回 nil
and we know that draw random card returns nil,
根据实现 它在 deck 为空时会返回 nil
if you remember from our implementation it returns nil when the deck is empty,
很完美
so, perfect!
为 nil 时 牌就不会翻到有内容的那一面了
Once it’s nil, it’s just not going to flip back over to the contents sides,
它会维持在反面
it’s going to always stay on the backside.
有问题吗
Question?
翻牌计数是不大优雅的第三个内容 如何修正呢
And flip count is the third thing that was kind of not very elegant, so how can we fix that?
这方面可以有多种解决办法
Well, you know, there’s a number of ways to go at that,
不过我认为最简单的是
but I think a simple way is to only
仅在真正翻动时才计数
flip, sorry, when we actually do the flipping over.
这其实并不是很棒的解决办法
Now, this is kind of not a great solution
因为这里 我们并没有实际翻牌
because here we’re not actually flipping over, you know, if,
如果我们在反面 那么这里我们要翻牌
if we’re on the card back, then we’re flipping over here,
这个不算很好 因为我们是在…
so this one’s kind of not so good, because we kind of gonna,
一旦翻到反面 我们没有问题 因为我们开始…
once we flip over to the back, we’ll be okay because when we start to do,
我们将反复执行这段代码
we’ll be executing this code over and over right here
因为我们总在背面
because we’ll always be on the back.
我认为这样能行 这是好的解决办法吗
So I think this’ll work, right? Is that a good solution?
我不喜欢它的原因在于
The reason I don’t like it is I don’t like having this line
一段代码同时出现在两处
of code in two different places, kind of eh.
我们还可以做很多别的事
I could have done a lot of other things here,
我们可以将图像和字符串提出到单独局部变量
we could have factored out the image and the string into separate local variables
用 if 应用这些 等等
and had our if, apply those, and stuff like that.
不过这些就有点过头了
I think all of that would have been a little bit of overkill.
我们来看看这能否奏效
So, let’s see if this works.
程序开始时 牌是朝下的
So here’s our thing here, so it started facedown.
点完整副牌
Let’s click through the deck here,
快速点它
I’ll click through it quickly.
可以看到 我点得很快
So I’m clicking so quickly through, you’ll notice
以致于动画都不能完全展示出来
that I’m not giving time for the thing to finish animating.
下下周我们会开始讨论动画
And we’re going to start talking about animation in the week after next.
动画中可能发生的一个情况就是
And one thing about animation is
它会同实际发生的情况有些不同步
it’s going to happen a little bit out of band with what’s actually happening.
这里我在快速翻牌
So I am actually flipping here and all that flipping is happening,
但动画却慢半拍 动画有些滞后
but the animation is kind of slow and it’s staying behind,
很不幸 它就是这样
and that’s kind of just, unfortunately, the way it is,
动画最终会赶上
the animation will eventually catch up,
这里我们到了最后一张牌
but here we go to our last card,
然后正面朝下 再点就没反应了
then we get facedown, and now we click, and it’s not clicking over
停在 104
and it’s stopped at 104.
关于这个解决方案有任何问题吗
Any questions about this solution?
很简单
Pretty straightforward.
优雅性 简洁性 这是你们在作业中要追求的
Again, elegance, simplicity, that’s what you’re shooting for in your homework.
加入很多 API 的复杂解决方案我们不推崇
Big, overwrought solutions where you’re adding a bunch of API and checking
我们推崇更简介优雅的解决方案
a lot of things are generally not preferred over more simple solutions,
就算像这样有两行做相同事情的代码
so like this, even if you have something where you kinda have these
都显得有些不够优雅
2 lines of code that are doing the same thing,
也许你不应该像这样复制
maybe shouldn’t be replicated like this,
这只能勉强算优雅
it’s a close call as to the really perfect elegance,
不过这里还要考虑简单
but I was going for simplicity here too
因为我只有这么多时间
because I only have so much time.
好
Alright.
下面 我们将要进入纸牌匹配游戏的下一阶段
So now, we’re going to go into doing the next phase of our card matching game,
也就是实际进行游戏
which is to make the game actually play.
游戏的进行是我们模型的一部分
Now the playing of the game is part of our model.
理解这个很重要
It’s really important to understand,
它不是控制器的一部分 而是模型的一部分
it’s not part of our controller, its part of our model.
因为我讲过 模型是关于游戏是什么
Because I told you that the model is the what your game is.
这是什么
Well, what is this?
这是一个纸牌匹配游戏 “什么”需要放在模型中
It’s a card matching game, so the what better be in the model.
所以 我们将在模型中创建一个类
So we’re going to create a class in our model
封装游戏进行的逻辑
that is going to encapsulate the logic of the game playing
它将对用户界面一无所知
and it’s not going to know anything about user interface.
它其中没有任何同用户界面相关的事物
It’s not going to have any things in it that have anything to do with user interface
这是一个非常重要的区分
and that’s a really important distinction to make.
我们来创建这个新类
So, let’s create that new class,
创建新类的方式同今天作业中一样
remember that we always create new class the same way you did with your assignment today
点击新文件
by saying new file.
我们想要一个 Objective-C 类
And we want an objective-C class and I’m going
命名为 CardMatchingGame
to call it card matching game.
它将继承自 NSObject 和所有基本类一样
And it’s going to inherit from NSObject as all of our kind of base classes do,
我将把这个类同模型中其它类放到相同目录下
and I’m going to put this thing in the same directory as the rest of my model
我还将用导航栏将它放到模型的同一个组中
and I’m also going to put it in the same group in the navigator as my model, as well.
它和所有这些一起在这个组中
So it goes with all these guys and it goes in this group.
记得这样做是很好的
It’s a nice thing to remember to do.
好 我们创建了它
Alright? So we create it.
这就是了
Here it is.
这是它的头文件
Here’s its header file right here and I’m going
我将使用这个自动对照 来显示实现
to use this counterparts, automatic counterparts, to show the implementation.
这是头文件及实现
So there is its header file and its implementation,
我在设计新类时 我总喜欢
and I always, when I design a new class, I always try
首先处理公共 API
to give my first crack at its public API first.
稍后再考虑它的实现
I’ll go do its implementation later,
我会先思考 人们会怎样使用我的类
but I want to kind of think of how are people going to use my class first?
以此驱动我的总体设计
Just to drive my overall design.
这里类很简单
And that’s for a simple class like this,
如果类更复杂一些
if you get into a more complicated class,
你可能需要同团队开意义重大的设计会议
you might be having significant design meetings which are teamed
来理解这是什么对象 它如何融入到世界中
to understand what’s this object, how does it fit into the world,
但如果只是一个简单直接的类
but if you’re just doing a simple straightforward class,
特别是在初次编写时
especially if you’re doing its first iteration,
有时 想想其 API 是什么就足够了
it sometimes nice to just think what is it’s API, we call it,
API 在这里也就是类的公共应用程序接口
okay, API is the Public Programming Interface for a class.
我需要思考这个纸牌匹配游戏需要做什么
So, I need to think of what this card matching game needs to do.
首先 我知道它需要一个初始化器
Well, one thing I know it needs is an initializer.
一个 init
An init.
当我考虑我的纸牌匹配游戏时
But when I think about my card matching game,
它有一些东西需要知道去初始化
there’s a couple of things it just has to know to initialize.
它不能只像 PlayingCardDeck 那样初始化自身
It can’t just initialize itself like a playing card deck can.
PlayingCardDeck 在开始时知道
A playing card deck knows everything it needs to know about
关于扑克牌堆它需要知道的一切
a playing card deck when it’s started,
但这个不知道这些
but this doesn’t really know that, so,
我需要一些东西 其中一个是
I need a couple of things. One thing I need is
玩家玩的有多少张牌
how many cards are we playing with?
玩家被允许总共匹配多少张纸牌
How many cards are, is the person allowed to match total?
总共多少张
Right? What’s the total amount of cards?
我们需要这个
So we need that.
所以这里我说 initWithCardCount(初始化 带纸牌计数)
So I’m going to say, init with card count,
这里使用 NSUInteger
and we’ll make an NSUInteger.
实际上 计数至少需要是 2 你们应该能想到
Really, that count has got to be at least two, you would think,
所以我在初始化器中 也许应该验证 确保它大于 1
so I’d probably, in my initializer, should check to make sure it’s greater than one
如若不然 我将从 self 返回 nil
and if it’s not I’ll probably return nil from self.
换言之 我将不初始化 我的 alloc init 会返回 nil
In other words, I won’t initialize, my alloc init will return nil.
确实 我们会选一种返回 nil 的方式
And we’ll, actually, we’ll pick one way where it does return nil,
但我们也应该验证这个
but we should probably check that too.
我需要的第二个东西是一个牌堆
The second thing that I need is a deck, a deck of cards,
因为我要发这些牌
because I got to deal these cards out, right?
我发牌后 你要选择一些来匹配
I’m going to deal them out and then you’re going to be able to pick some of them and do it.
所以这里我说 usingDeck(使用牌堆)
So, I’m going to say using deck.
(Deck *)deck
Deck star deck.
这里是初始化器
Okay, so there’s the initializer, and, of course,
为了这个 我需要导入 Deck
to do that I need to import deck, alright?
这很好
So that’s pretty good.
从这里开始
Start there.
我的游戏还需要什么
What else do I need for my game?
这是一个游戏 它当然应该有分数
Well it’s a game, so I think it should have a score.
这里用 NSInteger 来表示分数
Eh, we’ll say NSInteger score.
重申一次 使用 NSInteger NSUInteger
And, again, NSInteger, NSUInteger
而不用 unsigned int 只是风格问题
versus unsigned int is kind of a style thing,
上面用了 NSUInteger
I used NSUInteger above,
这里我用 NSInteger 保持一致
I’m going to use NSInteger to be consistent here
分数其实也可能为负
and my score can be negative possibly.
所以不是 NSUInteger 它可以为负
So that’s why it’s not an NSUInteger, it can be negative.
注意 这里我让该属性为只读
And notice I made this property read only.
我们第一次看到这个
It’s the first time we’ve seen that.
为什么呢
And why is that?
这是因为 我是游戏逻辑
Well that’s because I’m the game logic,
我需要决定分数是多少
I get to determine what the score is,
没人能够设置分数 我会告诉你分数是什么
nobody can set the score, I tell you what the score is.
因此 任何人都不能够设置该属性
Therefore, there should be no setter for this property.
至少公共上
At least not publicly.
等下你们会看到 私有上 我们可以改写它
You’re going to see in a moment, privately, we’re going to make this rewrite
从而进行私有设置
so that we can set it privately, right?
因为我们需要一直更新分数
Because we obviously need to be updating our score all the time
用户翻牌并匹配正确后会得分 我们需要更新
as people flip these cards over and get matches, they get points, we need to update it.
但公共上 我们希望它是只读的
But publicly, we want it to be a read only.
剩下我还需要解决一件事
The only other thing I need to do is
玩家需要点击这些牌 牌会翻面
someone’s going to be clicking on these cards; they’re going to be flipping over
它们被选择 可能会匹配
and being chosen and possibly matching,
所以我需要有某种方法 让玩家选择一张牌
so I need some sort of method to let somebody choose a card.
这里我将其称作 chooseCardAtIndex(在某下标处选牌)
So, I’m going to call this choose card at index,
还是 NSUInteger 类型 index
NSUInteger, again, index.
API 中有很多方式能让玩家选牌
So, there’s a lot of ways in API you could have for letting someone choose a card.
创建这一纸牌匹配游戏的对象 例如控制器
The person who creates this card matching game, not the person,
but the other object, like a controller
创建这一模型类的对象 知道计数
that creates this model class, knows the count,
因为它指定了牌的计数
because it specified the count of cards.
所以 这样指定一个下标很合理
So, it’s pretty reasonable to have them specify an index,
在 0 和这个 count-1 之间
between 0 and this count minus 1,
只要玩家选择了一张牌
anytime someone chooses a card.
这就是明确玩家选择哪张牌的一种简单方式
So this is just a simple way of specifying which card did the user choose?
类似地 我需要能够返回一张给定下标处的牌
And similarly, I actually need to be able to return a card at a given index,
为什么需要这样呢
and why do I need this?
因为我需要弄清游戏状态
Well, I need to be able to find out the state of the game
在任何时候 我需要知道
at any given time, I mean, how is my controller going
我的控制器如何为该游戏显示一个 UI
to display a UI for this game if it can’t, you know,
如果它无法弄清纸牌状态是怎样的 那就麻烦了
if it can’t find out what the cards, what the state of the cards is,
这里只是为了让它得到纸牌
so this is just a little way for it to get the cards,
它可以遍历所有这些纸牌 获得全部 全部更新
and it could iterate through all the cards and get them all, and update them all,
它也可以得到特定下标处的牌
or it can get one in a particular index
做它所需要做的最合适的事情
and could kind of, whatever fits best to what we’re doing.
好 这是我的公共 API
Alright, so, that’s my public API.
我在这里编写实现之前
Now before I go and do my implementation over here,
你们可以看到这里有一条警告 它怎么说
you can see that I got this warning right here and what’s this warning saying,
它说有三条 你可以点击这个 3 来展开
it’s saying there’s actually three of them, you can click on this little three by the way,
它说 你没有实现这些
it’s saying you have not implemented these,
你使之成为公共的三个方法 这个警告很好
these three methods that you made public, so that, that’s a good warning.
我需要这样做
I need to go do that.
但在这样做之前 我要先回到我的控制器
But before I do that, I’m going to go back to my controller,
我要展示给你们
I want to show you
这里我们需要有怎样的 UI
how we’re going to, what kind of UI we’re going to have over here so that
使得我们进行实现时
as we’re doing our implementation, you can kind
你能想象它们如何一同工作
of imagine how they’re going to work together,
但我不一定需要
but I actually wouldn’t necessarily have
在 CardMatchingGame 之前做这个 UI
to do the UI before I do the card matching game
有人甚至认为 我应该先做 CardMatchingGame
and one could argue I should do the card matching game first
设计模型时不要受 UI 太大影响
and not be influenced by the UI so much when I’m designing my model.
但是 要知道 这个模型将会同 UI 一同工作
But, you know, this model is going to be served by some UI
所以我们将一同做 让你们能够更好地想象
so we’re going to do them at the same time so you can imagine it a little better.
这个 UI 需要什么呢
So what do we need for this UI?
一点就是 我们需要很多牌
Well one thing is we need a lot more cards, okay,
这张牌无法和任何东西进行匹配
this one card, it can’t be matched against anything else,
让我们弄更多牌 这很简单
so let’s make more cards, this is very easy to do.
我只需要把这张牌移到角落里
I’m just going to move this card up into the corner here
然后复制粘贴 选择它 复制粘贴
and I’m just going to copy and paste it, so I can select it and copy and paste.
使用蓝色参考线来放置
Place it, use the nice blue guidelines there.
我还可以复制两张并粘贴
I can even copy two and paste them.
然后复制四张并粘贴
Or copy four, and paste them.
我将有 12 张牌 这是很好的纸牌数量
So now I’m going to have 12 cards, that’s a good number of cards.
实际上 我不再需要翻牌计数
I actually don’t need this flips thing anymore, I’m not going
这里不再是翻牌 而是要匹配
to be just flipping cards, I’m going to be matching cards,
也许我需要展示分数 但这是之后的事情
I’m probably going to need something for the score which we’ll do a little bit later.
不过这就基本上是我的整个 UI 了
But that’s pretty much my entire UI, I’m just going
我有这些牌 我将点击它们
to have these cards and I’m going to click on them,
它会显示出一张牌
it’s going to show a card and then I’m going,
然后我可以再点一下 让它正面朝下 取消选择
I could either click on it again to turn it back facedown, un-choose it,
我也可以点另外一张牌
or I could click on another card
如果匹配成功 我将得到一些分数
and if it matches I should get some points
否则的话 我之前选的那张将会翻回去 正面朝下
and if it doesn’t match, the other one, the last one I had is going to flip facedown.
这同你们所熟悉的 Concentration 游戏不同
Now those of you who are used to a game like Concentration, it’s a little different,
通常你选一张牌 然后再选另一张
usually you pick a card, then you pick another card,
相匹配你会得分
and if they match you get points,
否则两者都会翻回去
if they don’t match they usually both turn back over.
这是很酷的 UI 但我还没教你们怎么做动画
Which would be a cool UI, but I haven’t taught you how to do animation
这是这里所必须的
and that’s what you would need there
因为第二张牌需要正面朝上 在屏幕上显示一段时间
because that second card, when it comes up, would need to be on screen for a little bit
然后两者才会同时翻回正面朝下
before they both went down
因为这个你需要看一段时间
because you got to at least get to see this one.
因为你们没学过动画 所以点击第二张牌时
So since you don’t have animation, when you click on that second one, it’s going
如果不匹配 我们将让之前那张正面朝下
to facedown the previous one if they don’t match.
然后你不断点击
And then you just keep clicking around trying
找到相匹配的牌就能得分 我来展示下
to find matches and you get points, and we’ll show you,
我要使用的分数系统
kind of the point system that I’m going to use.
这就是我的整个 UI
So this is my entire UI.
这是一个非常以内容为中心的 UI
Very, it’s a very content-central UI, right?
UI 集中在这些纸牌上
The UI is really focused on these cards, there’s not a lot
周围没有很多装饰
of adornments and other stuff around it.
实际上 也几乎没有别的东西了
And we’re really not going to have much other stuff except
除了分数 你们还需要加一个重新发牌的按钮
for the score and you’re going to add like a redeal button
也许还有一些关于状态的内容 这些是作业
and maybe a little bit of stuff about some status about what’s going on in your homework,
不过 UI 的基础就是这些了
but this is the fundamental basis of the UI.
下面回到我们的 CardMatchingGame
So now let’s go back to our card matching game,
我们来讲讲如何实现这个
and let’s talk about how we’re going to implement this thing.
这里选择自动
I’m going to go back to automatic here.
把这个弄回来
Get this thing back.
为了让这更漂亮一些 我要这样
Just to make this look nicer, I’m going to go like that.
我将把这个头文件留在这里
And I’m going to leave this header file up while we go
同时来编写实现
and do the implementation so you can kind of see
这样你们就能对照着看 我们要做什么
where we’re shooting, this is what we’re shooting for.
首先我要让这个只在实现中为读写
So, the first thing I want to do is make this be readwrite in my implementation only.
做法是通过这个私有接口
And I do that with this little, private interface,
记得吧 这个我讲过 你可以使用
remember I showed you about this, that you can have one
这种开闭括号表示
of these with the little open parentheses, close parentheses
像这样 现在你可以声明你自己的东西
like that, and now you can declare your own things.
我将重新声明这个
Well, I’m going to redeclare this thing
为非原子 读写 NSInteger score
to be nonatomic readwrite, NSInteger score.
这个读写 我们不怎么使用 因为它是默认
Now this readwrite, we don’t use that very much because it’s the default, right?
isChosen 记得 Card 中的 chosen 和 matched 属性吗
Is chosen, remember the properties chosen and matched that are in card.
它们没说是读写 但它们有 setter 和 getter
Those didn’t say readwrite, but they had a setter and a getter.
它们是读写的
They were readwrite.
这个只使用在
We really only use this when we’re trying
重新声明公共中的只读为私有中的读写时
to redeclare a readonly one from public to private,
这是我们使用这个的唯一情况
this is about the only time we really use this.
也有一些编程风格
There are probably programming styles
有人喜欢一直加上读写
where people put readwrite all the time,
虽然这是默认 有些人对强是这样做的
even though it’s the default, some people do that with strong
强也是默认
since strong is the default.
我就喜欢在任何地方都指明强
I like to specify strong everywhere just
这样我脑袋里能更清楚知道发生了什么
so it’s really clear what’s going on in my mind.
但读写一般都没必要特别指出 除了这里需要重新定义
But readwrite, not necessary for most things except for here where we’re redefining it.
大家都理解这里我做了什么吗
So everyone understand what I’m doing here?
这是 score 和前面完全一样的分数
This is score, this is exactly the same score,
也就是说 这里将会有 setter
it’s just that this says there’s going to be a setter,
但我只能在私有条件下调用 setter
but I’m only going to be able to call that setter, at least not
至少在实现中编译器不会提出警告
without a compiler warning in my implementation.
因为我这里声明了读写
Okay, because I declared the readwrite part here.
没有公共理由能够设置这一分数
No public person is going to be able to set the score,
调用 setScore 而不让编译器提出警告
call set score, without compiler giving a warning.
下一步 我想考虑这个纸牌游戏的内部数据结构
So the next thing I want to do is
I want to think about my internal data structure for my card game
非常简单
really simple,
不过是一个纸牌的数组
it’s just an array of cards.
我将有一个纸牌的数组
I’m going to have an array of cards,
它将有这么多张牌 我将从牌堆中抽出它们
it’s going to be this many cards, I’m going to pull them out of this deck,
玩家将能选择这些牌 可以看这些牌
and, people are going to be able to choose those cards, someone can go look at the cards,
我们会在玩家选择对牌时进行加分
and we’ll adjust the score as people choose the cards.
我需要这种内部数据结构 这是内部的
So I need that internal data structure, it’s internal,
所以这里我需要说 非原子 强
so I’m going to put it here, nonatomic, strong.
它将是一个可变的 NSMutableArray
It’s going to be an NSMutableArray.
这同我们在 Deck 中看到的情况类似
And this is similar to what we had in deck.
这里我总喜欢注释一下 说是 Card 的
Alright? And I always like to put of card just to say what’s
因为 我说过
in here because as we said,
Objective-C 没有办法让编译器强制说这里是什么
there’s no way in objective-C to kind of have the compiler enforce what’s in here.
位于这个可变数组中的不过是对象
The things that are in this MutableArray are just objects.
编译器不知道它们是什么类
And the compiler does not know what class they are.
所以你需要确保没有将消息
So it’s up to you to make sure you don’t send messages
发送给错误的事物
to things you pull out of it that are wrong.
这里我们至少要让读代码的人知道我们的意图
So here, we are trying to at least give the person reading our code know our intent,
我们希望这里是纸牌的数组
our intent is for this to be an array of cards.
当然 我们希望进行惰性实例化
And, of course, we want our lazy instantiation.
这很好
So that’s good.
现在我们有了这个纸牌的数组 我们可以随时使用它
So now we have this array of cards, we can use it anytime we want.
还是那句话 我们可以在初始化器中进行这个初始化
Again, we could do this initialization in the initializer, right,
我们可以在这里做这个 alloc init
we can do this alloc init in here,
不过我更喜欢惰性实例化
but I happen to like using the lazy instantiation, I think it,
我认为它让初始化器的代码看起来更简洁
it’s kind of, makes the code in our initializer look a little cleaner.
下面让我们来写初始化器
So let’s do our initializer next though.
我将要复制粘贴
So I’m just going to copy and paste here.
也许没必要复制粘贴
You know, it probably not necessary to copy and paste
因为键入时 它会自动补全
because if you just start typing this, it’s going to complete it,
其它方法中 我会展示这个的
we’ll do that with the other method just to show you that one.
然后 我们都知道我们做了这个奇怪的事
And then we all know that we do this weird thing here,
self = [super init]
self equals super init.
这是我们类的指定初始化器
Now, this is our classes designated initializer,
换句话说 你需要调用这个初始化器
in other words, you have to call this initializer
否则我们的类将无法正常初始化
or our class will not be properly initialized,
我们可以有其它能调用这个的初始化器
we can have other initializers that could call this one, okay,
如果有方法能够默认设置这些
if there were ways to default things or whatever.
这里没有办法默认设置
There is no way to do that, default it,
所以这个必须是我们的指定初始化器
so this has to be our designated initializer, so,
我将在公共头文件中加一段注释
I’m actually going to put a comment in my public header file
注明这是我的指定初始化器
saying this is my designated initializer.
这样任何为 CardMatchingGame 编写子类的人
That way if anyone ever subclassed my card matching game,
就知道在他们的指定初始化器中
they would know that in their designating initializer,
他们需要调用 super 我们的指定初始化器
they’d have to call super, our designated initializer.
这就是指定初始化器的工作方式
Okay, that’s the way designated initializers work.
你需要从你的指定初始化器
You have to call your super designated initializer
调用你的 super 指定初始化器
from your designated initializer.
有问题
Question?
指定初始化器吗 不 编译器不知道
Designated initializer? No, the compiler does not know.
这纯粹是注释 它类似于这类注释
This is a purely commented thing, it’s similar to this kind of comment thing.
很不幸 编译器不知道 没有关键字说
It’s unfortunate that the compiler does not, there’s no key word or anything
这是我的指定初始化器
that says this is my designated initializer.
你的问题提得早些
You had a question first here?
好 你讲
Okay, question?
你可以跟进我讲的 我不大理解你的问题
Well, follow up with me, I don’t understand the question.
如果有其它初始化器 我猜
If you have other initializers, I guess the,
你的问题是我怎样禁用另一个初始化器吗
your question is how do I disable another initializer?
对 哦 我知道你是什么意思了
Right. Oh, I see what you mean.
问题是 我能否有另一个初始化器
Yeah, you, okay, so the question is could I have another
指定初始化器 不是公共的
initializer, designating initializer not be public
而是私有的 再让事物调用它
or something be private and have things call from it?
当然 你可以那样做
Yeah, you absolutely could do that,
只是 如果你让指定初始化器不是公共的
although if you make your designating initializer not public,
那么子类就不知道它
then subclasses don’t know about it
因为 Objective-C 中没有 protected
because there’s no protected in objective-C,
所以任何子类需要的东西都要设为公共的
so anything subclassers need has to be made public
来让它们看到它
for them to see it,
它仍在那里 仍然能够创建它的子类
it’s still there, they can still subclass it,
但要子类知道它
but, you know, to document it you want it,
你需要把它放到公共 API 中
you have to put it in your public API.
对 整个初始化器问题在 Objective-C 中
So. Yeah, the whole thing with initializers in objective-C is less
并没有很好地得到语言的支持
than nicely supported by the language.
请讲
Question?
问题是 这里是否可以
Yeah, so the question is would it make sense here to,
实现 init 在这里
for me to implement an init here, right?
来做点什么
To do something.
也许重写 init 也是可以的
And actually it might well make sense to override an init,
你知道怎么做吗
and you know what you would do?
返回 nil
Return nil.
因为如果你使用 [CardMatchingGame alloc] init
Because if you do card matching game alloc init,
它没有适当初始化
it’s not properly initialized
而且纸牌数或牌堆没有默认值 所以返回 nil
and there’s no default for the number of cards or the deck, so return nil.
对 答案是肯定的 你可以
So, yeah, so the answer is yeah you could.
好 回到我们的指定初始化器
Alright, so just back to our designating initializer,
我们需要调用 super 的指定初始化器
we need to call our supers designating initializer,
对于 NSObject 这是 init
which for NSObject is an init.
没有参数
No arguments.
然后我们可以说 if (self)
Then we just say if self,
这时我们可以初始化我们自己
then we can initialize ourselves
然后返回 self
and then we’re going to return self.
如果这里任何情况出现错误 我们将把 self 设为 nil
And if anything goes wrong in here, we will set self equal to nil.
从这里跳出来
Okay, and break out of this thing.
实际上 你们会看到 这里确实会出错
And, in fact, something is going to go in wrong in here, as you will see.
我们需要做什么来初始化这里的东西呢
So, what do we need to do to initialize our thing here?
我们需要从牌堆中抽出这么多张牌
Well, we need to pull this many cards out of this deck
将它放入我们的内部数据结构中
and put it in our internal data structure here.
怎么做到呢
Alright? So how do we do that?
这样做 for (int i = 0; i < count; i++)
How about for int i equals 0, i is less than count, i plus, plus,
这能让我遍历这么多个事物
so that’s just me going through this many of these things.
下面是 Card *card =
I’m going to say card star card equals
[deck drawRandomCard]
deck, draw random card,
这是从牌堆随机抽一张牌
so I’m drawing a random card of the deck,
然后我要说 self.cards[i] = card
and then I’m just going to say self dot cards, sub i, equals card.
我有这个可变数组 它将总是非 nil
So I’ve got this MutableArray, it’s always going to be non-nil.
这完全没问题
So this is perfectly fine.
不过这里有一个问题
There’s one problem here though.
如果牌用完了会怎样
What if we run out of cards?
如果传递一副扑克牌到这里
What if you pass a playing card deck here
然后你说要 100 张牌用于游戏
and you say 100 cards for your game.
这最终会返回 nil
This is going to eventually return nil.
牌不够
Okay, and run out of cards.
所以这里我们要检验说 if (card)
So we should check here and say if card,
然后再做我们一般要做的事
then we’ll do what we normally do,
否则 self = nil
otherwise, self equals nil,
并从 for 循环中跳出
break out of that for loop because we’re dead.
有问题
Question?
问题是 cards 中还没有任何东西时 我在这一行代码中
So the question is how can I access cards here to set it, in this line of
是怎样访问 cards 来设置它的
code, when I haven’t put anything in the cards?
cards 最开始时是 nil 然后当我调用 getter 时
Well, cards starts out as nil, and then when I call the getter,
这里 self.cards 是 getter 这会初始化它
self dot cards right here is the getter, it’s going to initialize it
得到空数组 但数组可变
to an empty array, but it’s mutable.
所以我可以在这里添加对象 哦 抱歉
So I can add objects here, Actually, oh I’m sorry.
这里你是对的 不过这也没问题
You’re right about that, yeah, well, this is fine too,
也许更好的做法是 self.cards
but maybe a better way to do this is to say self dot cards
addObject:card 这样更清楚一些
add object card, because that’s a little clearer.
也许你是对的 我的做法可能无法工作
In fact, you might be right, that wouldn’t have worked.
这是更好的做法 将纸牌加到牌堆中
So, this is a better way to do it, we just add cards to the deck.
好了吗
Make sense?
抱歉 之前我的那个不怎么好
Sorry about that, I had a little different one.
实际上 我不知道之前那个能否工作
And actually I’m not sure if that would work,
我来想想 你说的是插入对象
let me think about that, so you’re saying insert object,
这可能也能工作
yeah, that, actually that probably would work too.
因为你做的是在某下标处插入对象
Because you’d be doing insert object at index, it wouldn’t be,
这会是在数组最后 这也许也能行
you know, it would be just at the end of the array, that would probably work too.
两种方式都行
So you could do it either way.
因为 self.cards[i] 这里的下标 i
Because self dot cards sub i, that sub i thing,
调用的是一个方法 insertObject
it’s really just calling a method, insert object
atIndex 在特定下标处插入
at substring index, that’s what the method is calling.
你可以参考说明文档 看这里调用的方法名称
You can look at the documentation to see the name the method is calling there,
如果是在数组最后的下标处插入对象 我想这能行
but if you insert object at index and it’s at the end of the array, I believe that’ll work.
但如果是在下标 500 处 这也许就行不通了
But if you do it at 500, that’s not going to work.
因为数组只能逐渐增长 我这么认为
Because it can only grow the array as you go, I believe.
请讲
Question?
问题是 能否将不同类型的对象
So the question is can I put different kinds of objects
加到相同数组中 答案是当然可以
in the same array and the answer is absolutely.
我们有时确实也会这样做
You can and we do, occasionally, and we’ll talk
周三我会讲到如何处理这个
about on Wednesday how you deal with that.
考虑该如何处理
Right? How, how we manage the fact
不同类型的对象在这里
that we have different kinds of objects in there,
你讲得没错 这完全合法
but yes, absolutely, perfectly legal.
好 这是这个
Alright. So there’s that.
我说过 我们还可以在最开始这里说
And, again, as I said, we could probably say at the beginning here,
if (self)
if self,
我们还可以有 if count <2
we could also have an if count is less than two, right?
这时返回 nil 我们也可以检验这个
Then return nil, we could do that, check that, as well.
好 我们再来看一些别的方法
Okay, let’s do some of our other methods here.
来看 chooseCardAtIndex
How about choose card at index.
我们先来看 cardAtIndex 吧
Actually let’s do card at index.
因为 cardAtIndex 超级简单
Because card at index is super easy.
这里是 Card * 注意当我键入时
Right? This is card star, and notice if I start to type here,
它知道这是 cardAtIndex
it knows that its card index
它会自动补全 点 Tab 键就行了
so it’s going complete that, I press tab to get there,
这个只是返回 self.cards[index]
and this one it just returns self dot cards sub index.
但是 你知道 这是一个公共方法
But, you know, this is a public method.
如果有人传递了糟糕的 index 怎么办
What happens if someone passes a bad index there?
例如大于 count 的 index
An index that’s greater than the count.
我们这里会崩溃掉吗
Are we just going to go ahead and crash here?
有些人认为这很好 因为能够帮我们找 bug
One could argue that might be good, because we’ll help find the bug.
显然 这里有某种 assertion 会更好
Certainly some kind of assertion in here would be good,
我以后会讲到这个
we’ll talk about that later,
不过这里我将加一些保护 也就是
but I’m actually just going to protect myself against it by saying if self,
如果这个 index 小于 self.cards count
if this index is less than self dot cards count,
我就返回
then I’ll return.
否则… 噢
Otherwise, oops,
if… 我还是用传统的? 方式吧
if, actually we’ll do it this way, use the old question mark.
有些人曾问过这个
Some people were asking about this.
返回 问号 nil
Return question mark nil,
大家都知道这种问号冒号 C 语言做法吗
everyone know this question mark colon c thing,
这完全是非对象的 C 语言做法 对吧
this is totally a c thing, nonobjective c thing, alright?
就像 if then 一样
Just like an if then.
有问题
Yeah, question?
学生：[声音不清] 带有这些方法的数组访问
> So [inaudible], how does array access with these methods
如何让可变数组在没有保护下工作
for the MutableArray to work without that index, if you, or without the guard,
要是传递一个大的下标 它不会崩溃吗
if you pass the large index, would it necessarily crash or would?
老师：好 问题是
> Yeah. So the question is,
如果这里传递太大的下标 是否会崩溃
what if I pass too large an index here, would this crash?
它会 而且异常将是数组下标越界
And it would, and what would happen is it would crash
with the exception array index out of bounds.
不 不 它会崩溃
No, no, it would crash, it,
它会引发数组下标越界异常
raise an exception, array index out of bounds.
NSArray 类会引发这一异常
NSArray class would raise that exception,
我们会谈到异常引发机制的
and we’ll talk about raising exceptions.
现在 直到周五考虑调试之前
For now, until you go to this debugging thing, maybe on Friday,
你将只会看到异常出现在控制台中
for now, you’re just going to see exceptions like that happen on your console,
它甚至不会停在异常发生的地方 这很不幸
it’s not even going to stop where the exception happened, which is unfortunate,
不过讲调试时 我会讲到如何让它停止
but that debugging session, we’ll talk about how to make it stop there,
不过这就是会发生的情况 会引发异常
but that’s what’s going to happen, it’s going to raise an exception.
这是 cardAtIndex 非常非常简单
So that’s card at index, really, really easy.
下面再看另一个 即 chooseCardAtIndex
And now let’s talk about this other one, choose card at index.
这是我们逻辑的核心
This is really the heart of our logic.
因为这里是选牌的地方
Because here’s where you’re choosing the cards,
这是匹配和得分实际发生的地方
here’s where the matching actually has to happen, in the scoring.
所以我们的整个逻辑都将发生在这个方法中
So this is basically our entire logic is going to be in this method.
这里需要什么呢
So what do we need here?
玩家会选一张牌
Well, they’re choosing a card,
让我们获得玩家所选的牌
so let’s get the card they chose, and I’m going
我将调用 self cardAtIndex 来获得这张牌
to call self card at index, to get that card.
这样我就有了玩家所选的这张牌
Okay, so now I have the card that they, they’re choosing here.
如果玩家所选的牌已经同另一张牌相匹配
Now, if a card that they chose has already been matched against another card,
这里就什么都不用做
then I’m going to do nothing here.
当玩家去选已经匹配过的牌时 我将忽略玩家的行为
I’m going to ignore when you try to choose a card that’s already been matched,
successfully matched with another card,
这里我要的是
so I’m just going to say here,
if (card.isMatched)
if card is matched,
我要说的应该是 if (!card.isMatched)
and actually I’ll just say if not card matched,
我们会做点什么 否则我们什么都不做
we’ll do something, otherwise we’ll just do nothing.
只在你选的牌没有已经匹配过时
So I’m only going to match these cards if, or only going
我们才会尝试去匹配两张你选的牌
to try and match two chosen cards if the card you just chose is not already matched.
大家都明白了为什么要这样做吗
Does that make sense? Does everyone see why we do that?
已经匹配过的 就不能再同别的牌匹配了
It’s already matched, you can’t match it against another one.
然后的问题是 如果纸牌已经被选
So now the question is if the card is already chosen,
那我将怎么做呢
then what am I going to do?
这时我将把纸牌翻回去 取消选择
Then I’m actually going to flip the card back over, un-choose it,
所以这里我说 card.chosen = NO
so I’m going to say card dot is, dot chosen, rather, equals no.
如果选择了已经选过的牌
So if you’d pick the card that’s already chosen
两次选择 等于取消选择
and you choose it again, it’s going to un-choose it.
这是一种开关
So it’s kind of a toggle.
选牌是在选择和未选择之间来回切换
Choosing a card is kind of a toggle thing, on and off.
注意我们有 getter isChosen
Notice that we have the getter is chosen,
记得吧 我们在头文件中改名过
remember we renamed it in our header file,
通过 getter = isChosen
with that getter equals is chosen,
但 setter 不用 isChosen
but the setter, okay, we don’t use the is chosen.
setter 仍然是 chosen chosen 是属性名
The setter is still chosen. Chosen is the name of the property.
大家都记得吗
Everyone remember that?
来自 Card 你们需要键入这个 所以请记住
From card, hopefully, you had to type it in so remember it.
否则 我们到这里
So otherwise we’re in here
这种情况下 我们选择了一张新纸牌
and in this case, we’re choosing a new card and we need
我们需要将它同其它纸牌进行匹配
to match it against other card.
这里写 另一张牌
Let’s say another card.
我们的匹配游戏只匹配两张牌
Now our matching game only matches two cards.
你们的作业中 需要扩展到匹配三张牌
In your homework, you have to extend this game to match it to three cards.
这是你们作业的一部分
That’s going to be part of your homework assignment,
但这里 我们只匹配另一张牌
but here we’re only going to match one other card.
所以 这里我只需要检查纸牌数组中的所有其它牌
So all I need to do here is look through all the other cards in my cards array up here,
在这个内部数据结构中
alright, this is my internal data structure.
我只需要检查所有这些 看看
I just need to look through them all and find, and go and see
有没有另一张牌被选了 但没有匹配的
if there’s another card that is chosen and not matched.
如果有 我将把它同刚选择的这张匹配起来
And if it is, I’m going to try to match it against this card that was just chosen.
我将搜索所有的牌
So to search, I’m just going to go through my cards,
for (Card *otherCard in self.cards)
for card other card, in self dot cards.
遍历所有其它牌
And we go through all the other cards,
如果能找到另一张牌 已经被选 而且没被匹配
and if I can find an other card that is chosen and is not matched,
那就中了
then bingo!
我找到了另一张牌匹配上
I found another card to try and match.
这里只能有另外一张
Now, there can only be one other one,
因为我总是只考虑两张牌的匹配
because I only do two card matches and I’m always looking
我只检查第二张牌 如果不匹配
for that second match, so, if it doesn’t match,
我将把它翻回去 取消选择它
I’m going to flip that, un-choose that other one anyway.
这里我准备好了
So, I’m ready to go here,
这里只用找到另外一张能进行匹配的牌
I basically found the only other possible card that can match.
这里如果你要做三张或 n 张牌的匹配
Now, again, when you do a three card match or an n-card match,
作业中考虑 n 张牌可能会是一个好主意
if you so choose in your homework, which might be a good idea,
你会找到多张牌
you might find a number of cards here.
你可能需要用数组这些来收集
You might have to collect them somehow in array or something
这样你就能将它们进行匹配 但这里
so you can match them against each other, but here,
我不需要担心这些
I don’t have to worry about that.
找到了另外这张已经选择的牌 我们来进行匹配
So I found this other card that’s also chosen, let’s match them.
通过代码 matchScore =
And I’m going to do that by saying match score equals
上面这里玩家所选的牌 card
the card that we chose up here, right? This is the one that the user is choosing.
match: 记得吧 这是 Card 中匹配两张牌的方法
Match colon, remember that’s our method in card that matches two cards.
它的参数是一个数组
It takes an array though, an array,
我将现场创建一个数组 将另一张牌放入其中
so I’m going to have make an array on the fly and put the other card in it.
大家都明白这行代码吗
Everyone understand this line of code?
我在用 Card 中 match 方法将这张牌同这张牌进行匹配
I’m matching this card against this card using the match method in card.
但我需要现场创建这样一个数组
But I had to create this little array on the fly
因为 match 实际能够匹配多张牌 这很好
because match is actually capable of matching multiple cards, which is good
因为你们的作业中需要这个
because your homework’s going to require that.
但这里我只用考虑一个 所以这里
But here I’m only doing one, so I just create this little,
只需要一个蓝色 @[] 来创建数组
blue at sign square brackets thing to create an array.
这里有了这个 match
So now I’ve got this match.
我们定义过 match 的语义
Now, we’ve defined match, kind of the semantics of match,
如果返回的是非 0 那就有了某种匹配
are that if it returns non-zero, then there was a match of some sort.
如果返回 0 就没有匹配上
If it returns zero, no match.
这就是 match: 的意义
That’s what match colon means.
这就是我们对模型语义的定义
Okay, that’s what we just defined it that way in the semantics of our model.
也许在 Card.h 中应该加一小段注释
Probably we should have put a comment in our card dot h
说 match: 如果没有匹配返回 0
that says match colon, return zero if no match,
否则考虑匹配有多好
otherwise, how good a match it is basically.
如果匹配得很好 match 会返回高分
So match should be returning high scores if it’s a really good match
如果匹配不好 则会返回低分
and a lower score if it’s not so good a match.
这就是它的语义
You know, that’s kind of the semantics of it.
匹配上或没匹配上应该怎样呢
Alright, so, what if it is a match or it’s not a match.
这两种情况我们都需要处理
We have to deal with both of those cases.
在匹配上的情况下 我们将给自己分数
Alright, so in the case that it is a match, then let’s give ourselves that score.
而且两张牌都匹配上了 我们将它们标记为已匹配
And, both these cards matched, so let’s mark them both as matched,
所以这里说 card.matched = YES
so we’re going to say card dot matched equals yes,
而且另一张牌 otherCard.matched = YES
and the other card dot matched equals yes.
它们匹配上了
Alright? So they’re matched,
它们使命完成 我们得到一些分
they’re out of the game, we got some points.
如果没匹配上呢
Now what if they don’t match, well I told you
我说过 这时我会将选择的另一张牌取消选择
if they don’t match, I’m going to turn that other chosen card, I’m going to un-choose it,
所以这里有 otherCard.chosen = NO
basically, so I’m going to say other card dot chosen equals no.
而且 我还想因此罚一些分
And also, I think I’m going to impose a penalty for doing this.
我将从 score 中减一些分 这叫作错匹配罚分
I’m going to subtract something from the score, I’m going to call it my mismatched penalty
我将它设置为一个常量
here and I can make a constant.
我来简单讲一下常量
Now, let’s talk a little bit about constants.
要知道 这是 C
You know, this is c. Okay?
你可以按照 C 的方法来处理常量
So you’re going to make these constants however you want.
一种做法是用 #define
One way to do it is to say pound sign define, right?
我可以说 #define MISMATCH_PENALTY
So I could say pound sign define, mismatched penalty.
我们可以将 MISMATCH_PENALTY 设为 2
And we can make the mismatched penalty be, you know,
the mismatched penalty, what did I decide, I think something like two,
如果错匹配 我将罚掉 2 分
so I’m going to take away two points if you mismatch,
这是一种做法
so that’s one way to do it.
另一种处理常量的方式是用 const
Another way to do constants is const,
这里可以是 static const
okay, its static const even.
static const int MISMATCH_PENALTY = 2
Static const int mismatched penalty, if equals two.
这是另一种方式
So that’s another way to do it.
你可以随喜好选择
This is kind of as you prefer.
static const 的好处在于它们具有类型
The nice thing about these static const’s is they’re typed.
#define 没有类型 只是替换
Whereas a pound sign define is not typed, it’s just substituting.
而这里有类型 这在调试器中更好
But here you’ve got to type in and you’ll be able to see this in the debugger better.
因为它有类型
Because it’s typed.
不过你们可以根据喜好来
But it’s really kind of your own thing,
我只想说 不管你选择用哪种
I would just say be consistent about what you choose
#define 也好 static const 也好 请保持一致
to pound sign define versus what you decide to make a static const.
用哪种取决于你
Totally up to you.
另外我还要做一件事 如果你匹配上
You know, the other thing I’m going to do here is if you match, I actually,
毕竟这里错匹配会罚 2 分
since I’m basically charging you two points if you mismatch,
如果你匹配上 我会给你很多分
if you match I want to give you a lot of points,
所以我要给你一个匹配红利
so I’m actually going to give you a match bonus.
MATCH_BONUS
Match bonus.
这将是另外一个常量
And this is going to be another constant here.
放在这里 复制粘贴这个
Put this up here, actually let’s copy and paste this over
把这个贴过来
this, paste,
我将给你匹配分数的四倍
and I’m going to give you four times whatever your matching is
因为这里有罚分
because I’m giving you this penalty so I want
所以匹配上了我要多给点分你
to give you a bonus if you actually match.
不管匹配得分是多少 不管匹配有多少
So whatever the match score is, however good a match it is,
这里得到的分数都会乘以 4
you’re going to get four times as many points if you match.
这些东西你们可以自己去倒腾
And these are things that you would want to tweak
也许在你们的作业中 你们想要
or maybe, like, possibly in your homework, you might even want
把这些红利和罚分设置为公共 API
to make these be public API to set these bonuses and penalties.
让它们可以被设置
Maybe that’s something that wants to be settable,
为了简便起见 这里我们把它们设为常量
but we’re going to make them constants for expediency in our game.
另外一点是 如果我们找到了这个匹配
The other thing we can do here is if we find this match,
我们就可以从这个 for 循环中跳出来
right here, we can break out of this for.
这是因为这里只需要匹配两张牌
And that’s because we’re a two card matching game,
一旦找到匹配的 这就搞定了
once we found a match, we’re, we’re done.
我们找到另一张已选牌 处理掉它
We found another chosen card, we processed it,
我们不需要再找更多匹配的牌
we don’t need to keep looking for more matching cards.
作业中 当要匹配的数量多于 2 时
Again, if you have, matching more than two
你要将这些牌收集起来 这里就不能跳出
and you’re collecting cards, you may not be breaking out of this loop down here.
这里我还想做一件事 也就是
The other thing I wanted to do here is
如果你选择了一张牌 并让它正面朝上
if you are choosing the card and flipping it face up,
我要让它消耗一些东西
I want to make it cost something.
这里我要设置一些选择成本
So I’m actually going to give, make a cost to choose,
这里设为 1 分
and I’m going to make it be one point.
这是因为我不想让你
Okay, that’s because I don’t want you to be able to just,
没有成本地来回来回翻牌
you know, flip the card over, flip it back down, flip the card over, flip it back down,
最终记住所有牌 再翻过来让它们都匹配上
you’d eventually memorize all the cards and then flip them up and get all your matches.
这会有一些花销
So it costs you a little bit.
忘记牌的话 你需要重新翻开 这会花掉一些分
If you forget a card and you flip it again, it’s going to cost you just a little bit.
没有错误匹配扣分多 但还是会扣一些分
Not as bad as mismatching, but it’s going to cost you a little.
有问题
Question?
对 你是对的
Oh yeah, you’re right.
很好 我还得依赖你们提醒我哪里有错
Good call. See now I rely on all of you to make sure I don’t make mistakes
没错
like that, so yeah, absolutely.
这个 break 需要在这个 if 内
This break needs to be inside this if
因为当我们找到另一张牌时 我们会跳出这个 for
because we only break out of this for when we find another card.
提得很好
Good, good call.
最后当然是 我想要把这张牌标记为已选
The last thing, of course, is I want to mark this card as chosen.
抱歉这里用的是大写
And sorry for the caps there.
这张牌 噢 不是 isChosen 而是 chosen
This card, woops, not is chosen, chosen,
在做了所有这些之后 这张牌是已选的
this card is chosen after we’ve done all of this thing.
无论如何它都被选了 它是新的已选牌
In any case, it’s going to be chosen, it’s going to be the new chosen card.
它也可能已经被匹配 但它至少是已选的
It might also be matched, but it’s also chosen.
这就完了
So, that’s it.
这就是纸牌匹配游戏的整个逻辑
That’s the entire logic of my card matching game.
很简单 有点过度简化了
It’s pretty simple, it’s kind of in a way ultra-simplified.
你们可以想象复杂很多的情况
You can imagine much more complicated things, but,
不过这里我是现场编程
you know, I’m doing this on the fly here and we only have,
要知道 一堂课只有 1 小时 15 分钟左右
you know, an hour and 15 for, for lecture, so,
我故意弄得简单一些
I’ve kept it kind of intentionally simple,
不过我主要想让你们理解的是 这里没有 UI
but the main point I want you to understand from this logic is it has no UI in it.
这里只是处理纸牌 设置它们
Right? It’s purely just dealing with the cards and setting them
是否被匹配 是否被选
to be matched or not, whether they’re chosen or not,
取决于 match: 方法的使用 它也是我们模型的一部分
depending on using the match colon method, which is also part of our model.
这里没有 UI
There’s no UI here.
将这些逻辑传达给 UI 的是控制器
It’s up to our controller to take this logic and turn it into UI.
我们再来看看这个
So let’s take a look at that.
回到我们的串连图板 腾出一些空间
I’m going to go back to our storyboard here and make more space.
把这个移过来点
Move this over a little.
留出更多空间
Give me more space.
这是我们的控制器
Okay. So, here’s our controller, right?
之前我们写出了这个简单控制器
Our simple controller just as we had left it off,
我要把逻辑用到这个之中
and I need to use this logic in this thing.
首先我要做的是
So the first thing I’m going to do is
创建一个属性来容纳我的 CardMatchingGame
create a property to hold my card matching game.
有些人可能会把这叫作 model
Now, one could argue, some people would call this model,
我不大喜欢这样
I don’t like that so much,
因为 model 有时会扩展到多个属性
because sometimes a model will expand multiple properties
也有人会叫它 gameModel
or they might call it game model.
这不算太糟 我不反对这样
That’s not so bad. I’m okay with that.
我喜欢 game 我认为这样在代码中读起来更好
I like game, I think it reads a little nicer in the code, but,
不过这是一种个人偏好问题
it’s kind of a matter of personal preference,
无论如何 我需要导入我的 CardMatchingGame 头文件
but in any case, I need to import my card matching game header file here,
来让这个正常运行
to make this work,
我将惰性实例化它
and I’m going to lazily instantiate it.
如果 game 为 nil
I’m just going to say if the game is nil,
也就是说 我们的对象新初始化
in other words, just our object is freshly initialized,
那么我会让_game =
then I’m going to say game equals
[[CardMatchingGame alloc] init…
card matching game alloc, woops, game alloc, and then init,
这里有两个 init 一个继承自 NSObject
okay there’s two inits there, the one inherited from NSObject
我们知道它会返回 nil 所以我不想要这个
which we know is going to return nil so I don’t want that one,
另一个是 initWithCardCount
and init with card count.
我将使用这个 按下 Tab 这个游戏中有多少牌
So I’m going to do that one, tab over here, how many cards are in this game?
有 12 张
Well there’s 12.
所以这里应该键入 12 吗
So I should type 12 here right?
不对
Okay, no.
这就像在作业中使用 102 一样
That’s like putting a 102 in your homework solution, right?
以后我们可能增加牌数
We might add more cards someday,
这里绝对不要写 12 这里我暂时写 0
we absolutely do not want 12 here, so I’m going to put 0 here for now,
我到时会给你们展示 如何弄清这个值是什么
and we’ll, I’ll show you how we’re going to figure out what this number is.
usingDeck
And using deck,
幸运的是 这里我有 self createDeck
luckily I have self-create deck here,
所以我这样做
that’s why I did that that way.
这会创建我的牌堆
That’s going to create my, my deck.
然后我们返回_game 这很好地得到了惰性初始化
Then we’ll return underbar game and it’s nice and lazily initialized.
我们再来讨论一下这个 0
Alright, so let’s talk about this zero right there.
我们怎么知道这里有多少牌
How are we going to find out how many cards there are?
实际上 它有可能创建一个 outlet 到 UI 中的多个事物
Well it turns out it’s possible to create an outlet to multiple things in your UI.
记得吧 这里我们有这个 outlet
Remember that we have this outlet right here
flipsLable
flips label,
这是到下面这个 flipCount 的 outlet
which was an outlet that went to this little flip count thing, that we had down here.
它是一个单 outlet
It was a single outlet,
我们其实可以删掉这个单 outlet
which by the way, we can delete this single outlet.
但它只到一个对象 这个 UILabel 我们删掉这个
But it went to one object, the UI label, so let’s get rid of that,
我们不再需要 flipCount
and we don’t need flip count either,
我们也不再需要 deck 很多东西现在都可以删了
we actually don’t need deck either, there’s lots of stuff we can get rid of now.
我们将重新写这整个 删掉 setFlipCount
Alright, so we’re going to redo this whole thing, well, we’ll get rid of the setFlipCount.
这个等下我们会删掉
We’ll get rid of that in a second.
可以看到 现在游戏变得简单了很多
You can see our games gotten significantly simpler now
模型接管了这里的很多东西
that the model’s taking care of a lot of our stuff here
把这些都删除后 它会变得更简单
and it’s going to get even simpler when we delete all this.
无论如何 这是单 outlet
But anyway, that was a single outlet.
我们可以让 outlet 到多个事物
We can actually create an outlet to multiple things,
你们应该能够想到 这一 outlet 将是数组
and as you might imagine, that outlet will be an array.
如何做到呢
So how we do that?
很简单
Very simple.
方法和原来一样 我按住 Control 键
Exact same way, I’m holding down the control key.
选这张牌 按住 Control 并拖动到接口
Pick the card here, I’m going to hold down control and drag into my interface,
和之前创建 outlet 的方式一样 然后松手
just like I do with any other outlet I’m trying to create, and when I let go,
可以看到上面这里写有连接
you can see that at the top here where it says connection,
这里实际有选项可以创建 outlet collection
there’s actually the choice of making an outlet collection.
这是一个数组
So that’s an array of things.
这里还可以选 action 声明到这里
We can also make an action messenger, we’d be declaring it here.
或者到单个按钮的 outlet
Or an outlet to a single button,
但这里我要选 outlet collection
but here I’m going to do outlet collection
选 outlet collection 时 XCode
When you do do outlet collection, XCode,
不是 Objective-C 而是 XCode 希望知道
not Objective-C, but XCode wants to know,
这里有怎样的对象 这完全是 XCode 想知道
what kind of objects are in there, that’s purely for XCode, there’s,
我讲过 Objective-C 中没办法知道数组中是什么
I told you there’s no way to know what’s in an array in objective-C
编译器无法知道这个
and the compiler can’t know that,
这纯粹是为 XCode 准备的
so this is purely for XCode and you’re going
等下你们就能看到 XCode 是如何记住这个的
to see how XCode remembers this answer in a second,
这里是它的名称 我将其起名为 cardButtons(纸牌按钮)
and here’s the name, I’m going to call it card buttons,
这就是这些 这些是容纳所有纸牌的按钮
that’s what these are, these are buttons that are holding all the cards.
注意 这里没有问我是强是弱
Notice it’s not asking me strong or weak here.
这是因为这一属性必须是强的
That’s because this property has to be strong.
它必须是强的
And it has to be strong
因为视图虽然有一个强指针单独指向所有这些牌
because while the view has a strong pointer to all these cards individually,
但视图没有一个强指针指向这一数组
the view does not have a strong pointer to this array.
如果我们不将其设为强
And if we did not make this strong,
那么这就会被持续设为 0
than this would be constantly being set to zero
因为没人拥有强指针指向它
because no one would have a strong pointer to it.
所以这里需要是强的
So, that’s why this has to be strong,
因为它是数组 而不是一个按钮
because it’s an array, it’s not a button.
这一小段代码 会完全被编译器忽略
Now, this little stuff right here, compiler completely ignores this,
它同 IBAction 很像
it’s very much like IB action,
不过是 XCode 加到这里的一些东西
it’s just some stuff that XCode puts in there
让它自身知道这一特定属性是 outlet collection
so that it knows that this particular property right here is an outlet collection,
当我把鼠标悬停在这上面时
and you can see if I mouse over this
它会显示我放在这里的这个按钮
it shows me the one button that I put in here.
我倒想告诉你们 我们可以选择所有这些
Now, I’d love to tell you we can just select all of these
并 Control 拖动 但这是不行的
and control drag, but you can’t.
我一直希望有这种功能 但设计者从来就没提供过
I’ve been asking for that feature for years, but they never give it to me.
所以 我们需要一个个拖动
So, I have to drag these one-by-one,
有些不幸 但至少 你知道
it’s kind of unfortunate, but at least, you know,
我将它拖到已经存在的这个上
I drag it to the thing that’s already existing, and you notice
我靠近时 它会高亮显示合适的位置
as I get close, it highlights the thing that is appropriate and, again,
因为它知道这是按钮的 outlet collection
it knows that because it knows this an outlet collection of buttons,
所以这条属性会高亮显示
so that’s why I can highlight this property.
我将把它们都集中到这里
So I’m going to collect all of them here,
这样做时 有些容易犯错
and when you do this, you know, it’s somewhat error prone,
你可能会漏掉 所有最好是到这里来检验下
you might miss, so it’s nice to go back here and check,
你会看到所有 12 个按钮在这里
and you can see all 12 buttons in here.
有问题
Question?
问得很好 问题是 顺序要不要紧
Okay. Great question! The question is does the order matter?
顺序有没什么作用
Or is the order determined?
答案是没有
And the answer is no.
这里对象的顺序对你完全是未知的
This order, the order of the object here is completely unknown to you,
你不能依赖于它
and you cannot depend on it.
如果你需要顺序 你需要用不同方式来做
If you need the order, you’re going to have to do this a different way.
outlet collection 中顺序是未知的
Outlet collections are fundamentally, the order is not known.
所以不管我按什么顺序 Control 拖动它们
So no matter what order I control drag them,
这都不是数组中的顺序
that’s not going to be the order in the array.
苹果这样决定是很好的
Which was a good decision by Apple, it seems like oh,
也许你觉得这很好 但要放很多东西到这里
it’d be cool, but it’d be just too hard for them to, to throw a lot of things in here,
要显示太难 而且你会被弄糊涂
it’d be too hard to show and you could get confused,
所以你需要使用别的机制
so, you need to use something, a different mechanism, and you’re going
我们后面的课上 会讲很多能够做到这个的机制
to learn many mechanisms later in this class that you could do this with.
这里只是一个很简单的做法
This is just a pretty simple one right here.
对少量东西奏效
For a fairly small numbers of things.
无论如何 我们得到了到这些事物的连接
So anyway, we got this connection to these things.
现在 我们可以进行纸牌计数
So now we can do card count.
我们知道纸牌数量 我们可以说 self.cardButtons
We know the number of cards, we can just say self dot card buttons,
也就是这个属性 count
that’s this property right here. Count.
这就是这一数组中按钮的数量
So this is the number of buttons that’s in this array.
这很好 对我们而言很不错
So that was good. That worked out well for us.
有了这个很好的按钮数组之后 我们还可以更新它们
Now we also have a nice array of these buttons so that we can update them
配合模型中发生的情况
with what’s happening in the model.
首先 让我们来讨论触摸一张牌时 该怎么做
So, first though, let’s talk about touching a card,
when you touch on a card, what are we going to do,
显然不是这一堆垃圾 删掉这些
well we don’t want to do any of this junk. So we’re just going to rid of all of that.
因为我们要让模型来处理
Because we’re going to let the model handle it.
要让模型来处理 我们需要做的是
So all we need to do to let the model handle this is
获得这一按钮所关联的纸牌
to get the card that this button is associated with,
因为这些按钮仍然在发送这个
because these buttons are all still sending this,
看这个 12 个都在发送这个动作
if you look at this, see all 12 of them are sending this action
而发送器仍然是你实际触摸的按钮
and the sender is still the actual button you touched on,
不是数组 而是实际按钮
not the array, but the actual button,
因为这是这里的目标动作事物
because this is the target action thing right here.
我们仍然能够弄清 是谁发送的 实际上
So, we can still find out who sending it and, in fact,
我们甚至还可以找到它在这个数组中的下标
we can even find out it’s index in this array
通过如下代码 cardIndex =
by saying card index equals
[self.cardButtons indextOfObject:sender]
self dot card buttons, index of object, sender.
这将告诉我们
So this is going to tell us
这一发送按钮处在数组中什么地方
where this sending button is in this array.
这样我们就知道了它是数组中哪张牌
So now that we know which card it is in the array,
我们可以让游戏 选择那一下标处的纸牌
we can just tell our game please choose the card at that index.
我们会告诉我们的模型 嘿 选那张牌
And we’re just going to tell our model, hey, choose that card.
有一点要注意
Now, one thing here though is
选那张牌可能改变游戏状态
choosing that card might change the state of the game.
这会导致分数变化 或纸牌匹配
It might cause some points or match some cards,
很多东西会变
a lot of things can change,
所以这里需要 updateUI 来更新 UI
so we’re going to put a little update UI here.
这个 updateUI 方法
And this update UI method, which we’re going to have
等下我们会写 它会让 UI 同模型同步
to write has got to keep our UI in sync with the model.
记得吧 这是控制器的首要任务之一
And remember that’s one of the primary things a controller does,
它会同步模型和 UI
it syncs up the model with the UI.
这里我们来加一小段代码
So let’s go ahead and put a little thing here.
updateUI
Update UI.
更新 UI 时我们需要做什么呢
So what do we need to do when we’re updating this UI?
其实很简单 我们将遍历所有纸牌按钮
It’s actually pretty simple, we’re just going to go through all the card buttons.
获得那个纸牌按钮 同时在模型中观察相应纸牌
Get that card button, simultaneously look into the model for that card,
确保纸牌按钮展示出它所应该展示的纸牌内容
and make sure the card button is showing what should be on that card.
所以这里需要 for (UIButton *cardButton
So, let’s go for UI button, card button,
属于我们的 cardButtons 中 )
in our card buttons.
这里是遍历所有这些按钮
So we’re iterating through all these buttons.
carbButton 是迭代变量
Card button is going to be the variable.
让我们获取 cardIndex 还是一样
Let’s go ahead and get that card index, again, for the same thing,
self.cardButtons indexOfObject
self dot card buttons, index of object,
carbButton 是我们的迭代变量
the card button that is our iteration variable
这些东西明白了吗
and we’re cool with what we’re doing there.
我们弄清了这是哪张牌
Alright? So we’re just figuring out which card it is.
然后我们要让模型给我们那一下标处的牌
Then we’re going to ask our model, give us the card at that index,
使用 cardAtIndex
using card at index.
现在我们就有了纸牌按钮和纸牌 很棒
So now we have the card button and the card, awesome.
下面我们来确保纸牌按钮反映了纸牌上的情况
Now we can make sure the card button reflects the card that goes along with it.
我们需要在按钮上设置什么
So, what do we need to set on the button?
我们需要设置纸牌按钮的标题
Well, let’s see, we have to set the card buttons title.
这里是 setTitle:
So set title
forState:UIControlStateNormal
for state UI control state, control state normal.
我们还需要设置背景图像
And we have to set the background image.
取决于这里是斯坦福 logo 还是空白背景
Depending on whether it’s the Stanford logo or the blank background.
而且 如果纸牌已被匹配
Also, if the card is matched,
我将禁用按钮
I’m going to disable the button.
因为纸牌已经被匹配
Because you’ve already matched this card,
你不能再点它 我将禁用它
you can’t click on it anyway, so I’m going to disable it
因为禁用的按钮会略显不同
because a disabled button looks a little different
而我希望已匹配的按钮有所不同
and I want buttons that are matched to look different.
请讲
Yeah?
确实
It does.
问题是 这样的快速枚举
So the question is does a fast enumeration like this,
使用这种 for in 结构
when you do this for in thing,
是从 0 到 N 吗 答案是肯定的
does that go from the zero to the N and the answer, it does.
确实是按顺序来的
It does go in order.
你可以 问题是 这不是必需的吧
You could. So the question is do you, do you not need this,
你可以用别的迭代变量
you could just have another iteration variable
或者你也可以使用迭代变量 i
or you could use an iteration variable here,
如 for i = 0 to 长度
like for i equals 0 to the length?
你可以
You could.
我不喜欢用那种 0 到具体长度
I don’t like to depend on that going from 0 to whatever,
所以我使用这个 这是风格问题
so that’s why I used this here. It’s a matter of style.
完全是风格问题
Totally a matter of style.
而且这样更清晰一些
This is also kind of a little clearer,
因为这里我说 我想要
because here I’m saying I want the card that goes with,
这里的所有纸牌按钮
you know, the card button that goes with this thing.
最后我要说的是
So, so the last thing I’m going to say is
cardButton.enabled = !card.isMatched
the card button enabled equals the card, not card is matched.
只有纸牌没有被匹配时 按钮才启用
So, the card, the button will only be enabled if the card is not matched.
当然 我还有这两个东西没有提供
Okay, now of course I have these two things, which I haven’t provided, right?
我们还没有这些参数
I’ve just left them, we don’t have that argument.
实际上对于这两者
And actually for both of those,
我都将创建别的辅助方法
I’m going to create little other methods here, helper methods.
对于标题
So, I’m going, for the title,
我将创建一个辅助方法叫 titleForCard
I’m going to have a helper method called title for card.
它使用 card 作为参数
It’s going to take a card as the argument.
而且它会返回 card 的标题
And it’s going to return the title of that card,
背景我将使用 (UIImage *)
and for the background I’m going to have UI image,
backgroundImageForCard
background image for card.
但愿随着课程推进 你们能理解我们的命名惯例
Hopefully as we’ll go along you’ll start to see the naming conventions that we use.
我们通常会把冒号前名称的最后这部分
We often try to have this last part of a name of a method before a colon
用来表示我们要的东西
indicate what we’re looking for.
这里我们要的是一张牌
So here we’re looking for a card, so we try to make a thing.
再看这个 按钮 对吧 这是一个按钮
Look at this one, button, right? This is a button.
这里我们是在告诉代码的读者
So we try to make these arguments
我们想要放到这里的是什么参数
guide the reader towards what we’re asking for there.
对此 我们也不必太过拘泥
We don’t want to get too overwrought about it,
不过总的命名惯例就是这样
but it’s a general naming convention there.
一张给定纸牌的标题是什么
So, what is the title of a given card?
我有一张牌 它的标题是什么
So I have the card, what’s its title?
如果纸牌已被选择
Well, if the card is chosen,
那么我将返回纸牌的内容
then I’m going to return the contents of the card.
否则 我会返回空字符串或 nil
If it’s not, I’m going to return empty string or nil,
所以这里写 return card.isChosen
so I’m just going to say return card dot is chosen,
? card.contents
question mark, car dot contents,
否则
otherwise,
空字符串或 nil 这里都行
empty string let’s say or nil, either one in this case.
背景图像怎么办呢
And how about the background image?
这个很酷 这里我说 返回 UIImage
This is kind of a cool one, I’m going to say return UI image,
图像名为 card.isChosen
image name is card dot is chosen,
如果纸牌被选 那么我想要正面
so if the card is chosen, then I want the card front,
否则我想要反面
otherwise the card back,
你肯定会觉得 我很钟爱这种?: 语法
now you probably think I’m just in love with this question mark colon syntax,
我确实喜欢 它很简洁
which I do like it a lot, it’s kind of clean.
反正你们是懂的 对吧
But anyway, you understand what I’m doing here, right?
我在名称这里
I’m actually having the name in here
嵌套了?: 结构
with the question mark colon nested inside,
这样来获得图像
[inaudible] to get the, the image.
下面 我就可以将其用到这里了
So now, I can use that here.
首先是标题
Let’s do the title first.
这里我写 self titleForCard:card
I’m just going to self, title for card, the card,
然后这里我写
and then here I’m going to say
self backgroundImageForCard:card
self background image for card, card,
这两处我都加个回车 这样更清晰一些
and both of these I’m going to hit return just to make this a little easier to see.
这基本就算完了
So, that’s pretty much it.
我将 UI 同模型匹配了起来
I’ve matched up my UI with my model,
触摸 UI 时 我让模型知道去选一张牌
when I touch in the UI I let my model know to choose a card
我们基本上搞定了
and we’re pretty much good to go.
我想我要做的都做了 分数我等下再处理
I think that’s all I had to show, yeah, we’ll, we’ll do the score in a second here.
分数确实需要 但这之前
We need to score, but before we do the score, let’s go ahead
我们先来运行这个 确保它能工作
and run this and make sure that it’s working.
我点它 得到的应该是随机纸牌
Okay, so when I click, hopefully I get a random card,
再点它 应该得到相同的牌
and when I click again, hopefully it continues to be the same card.
如果总得到随机纸牌 那就糟了
It’d be bad if that was constantly getting random card,
但我们删掉了那部分代码 肯定不会是那样
but we know that we got rid of that code so it’s not going to do that.
这里是 K
So there’s a king,
然后是 5
five,
2 我们得到了两个梅花
two, okay, now we got two clubs right here.
我可以这样做 哦 不能匹配
So I could do that, oh, didn’t match.
为什么不能匹配上呢
So why don’t these match?
它们应该匹配上
They should match.
原因有人能够告诉我吗 请讲
And the answer, anyone want to tell me? Yeah?
正是
Absolutely.
我们唯一的匹配函数 是这个很糟糕的 match 函数
The only match function we have is this really bad match function,
我们来看看
let’s go look at it.
它在 Card 中 整个应用中就这唯一一个匹配函数
It’s right here in card, okay, this is the only match function
that exists in our entire application
它说 只有两张牌完全相等时才匹配
and it only says it’s a match if both cards are identical,
这在我们的情况中永远无法成立
well that’s never going to be true in our thing,
因为我们的牌堆中是 52 张不同的牌
because we have a deck of 52 cards, every single one is different.
这将永远无法匹配上 怎么解决呢
So it’s never going to match. So how do we deal with this?
我们需要告诉 PlayingCard 如何更好地匹配
Well we need to teach playing card how to be a better matcher.
因为 Card 对 match 的这种实现根本不够
Because cards implementation of match is simply not sufficient.
所以我们需要重写这个
So what we’re going to do is we’re going to override this,
我们使用面向对象编程
we use object-oriented programming,
我们在这里就是做这个 我将重写它
that’s what we’re here for, so we’re going to override it.
我们来到 PlayingCard 这是 PlayingCard
Let’s go to playing card, here’s playing card.
注意到 PlayingCard 没有在公共 API 中声明 match
Now, notice the playing card doesn’t declare match in its public API.
它是从 Card 中继承得到的
It inherits it from card
我不打算重新声明它 因为我只需要实现它
and I’m not going to redeclare it just because I’m going to implement it.
我将到这里重新实现 match
So I am going to go here and I’m going to re-implement match.
它知道 match 是我继承的方法
It knows that match is method I inherit,
因此 这里它能够自动补全
that’s why it was able to escape, complete it like that.
但我不打算把它放入我的公共 API
But I’m not going to put it in my public API
这就是我们的一般做法
and that’s generally the way we do it.
一般而言 如果你继承了一个公共方法
Generally, if you inherit a method and you, a public method,
你重写它 你就不需要再把它放入你的头文件了
and you override it, you don’t have to put it in your header again.
有些人的风格希望把它放到那里
Some stylistically would say, yes, put it in there,
这样别人就知道你在重写它
so that someone knows that you override it.
但大多数面向对象的人会说
But most object-oriented people would say
你不需要知道你重写了它
you shouldn’t have to know that you override it.
这是面向对象编程
Alright? This is object-oriented programming.
你无需知道这个
You should not have to know that.
你重写了 match 只是实现细节
That, that’s implementation detail that you happen to override match here.
我是不将 match 写到 PlayingCard 中的支持者
So, I’m a fan of the not putting match in playing card,
它已经在 PlayingCard 公共 API 中了
it’s already in playing cards public API
因为这会继承自 Card
because it inherits it from card.
match 中我们怎么做呢
Alright, so what are we going to do in match?
我这里随便弄一个
Well, I’m going to have a really dumb match.
你们在作业中需要设计个更好的
You’re going to need a better one for your homework.
我这个笨拙的 match 将只匹配一张牌
My dumb match only can match one other cards.
所以这里首先我要说的是
So and the first thing I’m going to say here,
int score = 0 以及 return score
let’s go ahead and do int score equals zero and return score.
然后我要说的第一件事是
The first thing I’m going to say is
if ([otherCards count] == 1)
if other cards count [pause] equals one.
我将只匹配一张牌
So I’m only going to match one other card.
有两张牌 则没有匹配
If there’s two cards in there, no match.
对我而言 太多了
Too, too much for me.
所以我只处理这一张牌
So I’m just going to say this one thing.
但我需要这另外一张牌 如何获得呢
Now, I need that other card though, how do I get the other card?
我要说的是
I’m going to say card star other, in fact,
PlayingCard *otherCard =
I’m going to say playing card star other card equals,
这里我可以做很多事
and I could do a lot of things here.
我可以说 otherCards[0]
I could say other cards sub zero,
但这里 我想使用一个我希望你们知道的方法
but I’m actually going to use a method here I want you to know
叫作 firstObject
called first object.
otherCards firstObject
Other cards, first object.
firstObject 返回数组的第一个对象
Okay, first object returns the first object in an array.
如果数组为空 它会返回 nil
If the array is empty, it returns nil.
这不同于 otherCards[0]
That’s different than saying other cards sub zero.
otherCards[0] 在数组为空时会崩溃
Because if that array is empty, that will crash.
导致数组下标越界错误
That will say array index out of bounds.
明白这种差别吗
You see the difference?
firstObject 还有 lastObject
First object, there’s also a last object,
它们有这种避免数组下标越界的额外功效
they just have this magic piece to them that they don’t do array index out of bounds.
firstObject 会返回第一个对象或 nil
But otherwise they return the first object or nil
如果没有对象的话
if there are no objects in there.
我想让你们知道这个
I just want you to know that.
这里其实并不需要这样
I don’t actually need that here,
因为我知道数组中有一个对象
because I know there’s one object in that array.
所以这里并不必要 我可以说 otherCards[0]
So this is not really necessary, I could say other card subzero,
这里没有问题 我只是
I’d be okay here, but I’m just trying
希望教给你们 firstObject 方法 仅此而已
to teach you the method first object, that’s all.
这就得到了另一张牌
So I got this other card.
我们来匹配它 好的匹配是怎样的呢
So let’s go ahead and match it, what’s a good match here?
如果花色匹配上 我会给一点分数
Well, if the suits match, I’ll give a little bit of points,
如果大小匹配上 我会给更多分数
but if the ranks match, I’m going to give a lot of points,
这里我说
so, let’s say
if ([self.suit isEqualToString:otherCard.suit])
if my self dot suit is equal to string the other card’s suit.
这是花色匹配的情况 例如都是梅花
So the suits match, they’re both clubs.
这时我将把分数 score 设为 1
Then I’m going to say the score equals one.
这里可以用 else 因为这里假设所有牌都不同
But, and we can say else or not, because we’re going to assume the cards are all different.
如果牌一样 只得到花色匹配的分数
So if the cards are the same, then you’re only going to get a suit match,
就会显得很荒谬
which doesn’t really make sense,
但这里没问题 再有 if ([self.rank])
but let’s say if self dot rank,
噢 这里不需要发送消息
oops, we don’t need to send a message there
if (self.rank == otherCards.rank)
if self dot rank equals the other cards rank,
那我们就给 4 分
then let’s give four points.
为什么是 4 分对 1 分呢
Now why do I give four versus one?
想想这里的数学
Well, think of the math, right?
你手里有一张梅花 牌堆里还有多少张梅花
If you have a club in your hand, how many other cards are there
in a full deck that will match a club?
12 张 如果我有一张 K 还有多少 K
12. If I have a king, how many other kings are there?
3 张
Three. Okay?
12:3 所以一整副牌中 匹配花色要容易四倍
So 12 versus 3, it’s four times easier to match that club, assuming you have a full deck.
这里我只是随机选的数字
I’m just picking numbers kind of at random here.
对于这里的评分 这并不糟糕
It’s, it’s not a bad choice for the scoring here,
不过多数时候相对分值不能搞错
but most times trying to get these relative scoring right.
有问题
Question?
问题是 这里我是不是使用了固定数字 正是
Yeah, so the question is am I using magic numbering and absolutely.
在我们的简单实现中 整个评分系统都是用的固定数字
And you probably, you know, this whole thing
of the scoring here is somewhat magic numbers in our simple implementation,
你也许…
you probably, although,
这里并不一定要是固定数字
this, okay, this is not necessarily a magic number.
如果你定义最简单的匹配得分为 1
If you define match to say make the easiest match verse, verse, equal one,
然后让更复杂的匹配
and then make any more difficult matches
是它的乘数倍 例如像这样更难的情况
to be multiplicatively, you know, more difficult like this,
那么这就是对的
then this is actually right,
因为这个 4 对于扑克牌是基本的
because that four is fundamental to a playing card,
这对于扑克牌的大小和花色是很基本的
it’s fundamental to how a playing card ranks and suits work, alright?
只要你定义的匹配
So, assuming you define this match
只匹配相同牌堆中的其它扑克牌
only match against other playing cards in this same deck,
这个 4 是固定的 但它对于这个类是固定的
that four is magic, but it’s magic to this class.
没错 你可以使用 #define
So, yeah, you could put a pound sign define,
但这并没有减弱它的固定性质
but that doesn’t make it any less of a magic number.
它是固定的 但你可以把它用到这里
So it is magic, but you could put it in there.
明白我说的了吗 明白差别了吗
You see what I’m saying, see the difference between that
这不同于控制器中的 102
like 102 in your controller
尝试把情况设置成通用的牌堆 这有些不同
which is trying to be maybe generic decks, that’s a little different.
问得很好
Good question though.
这样 我们有了更好的匹配
Alright, so now we have a better match.
下面我们回到控制器中
So now if we go back to our controller, so let’s do that.
回到这里的屏幕
Just back on screen right here.
然后运行
And run.
但愿这里我们能够找到匹配
Hopefully now, let’s see if we can find a match.
好 这里有张梅花
Okay, so there’s a club,
这里也有一张梅花 将它们匹配起来
and this is a club so let’s match them, ready?
哦 确实能匹配上
Oh! It matched!
而且禁用了这两个按钮
And it even disabled them.
但我不知道我得到了多少分
But I have no idea how many points I got
因为这里没有显示分数
because there’s no score on here,
显然我们需要分数 下面把分数加进来
so, obviously, we need a score, so let’s put the score in.
希望现在你们能够很容易地想象到
Hopefully by now you can imagine easily
我们应该如何加入分数
how we would do the score,
很简单 就像翻牌计数一样
simple, just like flips,
我们使用这里的标签
we just grab a label here
把它拖到这里 这里改成分数：0
and then drop it down in here, I’m going to say score zero,
因为这就是最开始我想要的分数情况
because that’s what I wanted, oops, that’s what I wanted to say when we start up.
确实 你可以在开始时加载这些字符串
And yes, it’s possible you could load these strings up at start up,
后面几讲中我会讲到代码中何时何地这样做
we’ll talk about when and where to do that in your code in the next couple lectures.
有了这个分数后 我显然需要能够同它通信
So I have this score, I obviously need to be able to talk to it,
于是我 Control 拖动到接口创建一个 outlet
so I control drag up here into my interface to create an outlet.
松手 这个应该是 outlet
I let go, this one wants to be an outlet,
不是 outlet collection 而是 outlet
not an outlet collection, but an outlet.
我将它称作 scoreLabel(分数标签)
I’m going to call it score label.
它可以是弱的
It can be weak
因为我们知道视图会指向它 它是 UILabel
because we know that the view is going to point it, it is the UI label.
这里有了它的 outlet
There’s an outlet for it.
我将在 updateUI 中更新它
I’m just going to update it in update UI.
所以这里我说
So I’m going to say
self.scoreLabel = [NSString
self dot score label equals NSString,
stringWithFormat:@”Score:%d”…
string with format, we’ll say score colon percent d,
分数从哪里得到
and where do we get the score?
有人知道分数从哪里得到吗
Anyone know where we get the score?
从 game 正是
From the game, exactly!
从我们的模型 self.game.score
From our model, self dot game dot score.
下面我来展示一下 确保大家理解了
Now I’m going to go show that just to make sure everyone understands that.
这是我的 CardMatchingGame
Here’s my card matching game,
记得吧 在它的公共 API 中有 score
remember that in its public API, it has the score.
选择时 我们会计分
And we’re keeping the score when we’re choosing.
大家都明白了吗
Everybody cool with that?
这就是了
So that’s it.
更新分数要做的事我们都做了
That’s all we need to do here, to update the score.
一般我们… 噢 这里需要 scoreLabel.text
Normally we have, oops, this needs score label dot text.
抱歉 我们需要 UILabel 类的 text 属性
Sorry. Alright, we need the text property of the UI label class
我们会调用它的 setter 设置 text
and we’re calling it setter here, set text,
这就是这里发生的情况 设置分数
this is basically what’s happening here and setting the score.
我还要做一件事
One other thing I’m going to do just
也就是防止分数太大 把这个拉宽一些 然后运行
in case the score is really big, so make that wide, and run.
我们以后会讲到 文本框如何
And we’ll talk about, by the way, text fields that get larger
随你输入的文本而增大
when you put text in them and stuff like that,
iOS 中有处理这个的方式
there’s a way to handle that in iOS, as well,
不过我们一次讲不了那么多内容
we’re not, we can’t talk about it, everything all at once though.
这里我们看看
Alright, so let’s see here.
-1
Minus one.
为什么获得 -1 分
Why did I get minus one?
因为翻牌是有成本的
Because I have a cost to flip.
每次翻牌都有代价
So every time I flip a card, I got to pay, alright?
这是黑桃 这也是黑桃 对吧
Now here’s a spade and here’s a spade, alright?
我点这个之后 分数会是多少
So what’s going to be my score after I click this?
点这个还是会花掉 1 分
Well, clicking this still going to cost me one, so that’s going
这会让我的分数减少为 -6
to make my score go down to minus six, but I’m going
但匹配正确后我能得到 1 分乘以 4 分的红利
to get one point for matching times my match bonus of four,
也就是 4 分
is four more points.
所以我的分数应该是 -2
So my score should be minus two.
对吧 确实也是
Alright? And it is!
很好 看看能否找到匹配的大小
Woohoo. Okay, and let’s see if we can find ranks that match.
哦 这里有个 6 这里也有个 6
Oh, there’s a six and here’s a six.
我将让这两个匹配上 分数会变成多少
Okay, so I’m going to make these two match, so what’s this going to be?
现在是 -9 点这个以后
Alright, so we’re at minus 9 now, when I click this one,
分数降到 -10 但它们会匹配上
we’re going to be at minus 10, but they’re going to match.
我将得到 4 分
I’m going to get four points
乘以 4 分的红利 总共得 16 分
for the match times my match bonus of four is 16 points.
因此分数将变成 +6
So I’m going to be at plus 6.
大家都同意吗
Everyone agree with that?
没问题 分数为 +6
And there we are, score plus six.
这就完了
Alright, so that’s it.
今天我要讲的就这些 最后还有一些幻灯片
That’s as much as I’m going to do and I’m, we got some slides here at the end,
不过 demo 就这些了
but that’s it on the demo here.
你们的作业是匹配两张或三张牌
And your assignment is going to be to make it
so you can match two cards or three cards,
你可以在 UI 中加一个开关
you can have a little switch or some sort of UI
在两张或三张牌的匹配之间切换
to choose between whether you’re matching two cards or three cards,
这需要模型中改变一些逻辑
and so that’s going to require some change to your logic in your model.
也需要更多一点的 UI
It’s going to require a little bit of UI and it’s going
还需要你的控制器将两者衔接起来
to require your controller to do a little bit of glue in between that.
你还需要在这里加一个标签 描述这里发生了什么
You’re also going to be asked to add another label in here that says what’s going on.
但我点这里时 它要告诉我 你选了红桃 7
So when I click this, it should say you chose the seven of hearts.
当我选这个时 它要告诉我
When I choose this, it should say
红心 7 和梅花 2 无法匹配上 -2 诸如此类
seven hearts and two of clubs did not match, minus 2, or something like that.
如果选了两张确实匹配的牌
So, if you pick two things that do match,
例如
like,
这两张红心
those two hearts,
它应该说 红心 4 和红心 7 匹配 得多少分
it should say four of hearts, seven of hearts match for whatever points.
有问题
Question?
如何在设备上测试它
How would you test it on a device?
我们在设备上运行一下试试 问得很好
Okay, let’s run this on a device actually. Great question.
这里我连了一个设备 你可以看到
So I have a device attached over here, which you can see,
它要求我更新 我们这里不会照做
and it’s asking me to update, which we’re not going to do right now,
在 XCode 上面 你会看到一些
and if you look up at the top of XCode, you’ll see that there’s a
不同的模拟器可供运行
bunch of different simulators you can run on
你还可以在连接的设备上运行
and you can also run on a device if you have it attached,
下周五我们或许将有一节课
and we’re going to have a Friday section probably next week,
或下下周 我们会为你展示
or maybe the week after, where we’re going to show you how
如何注册你的设备 并将所有这些设置好
to register your device if you don’t know how to do that and get this all set up.
这可以说是一个预览 我将在 iPad 上运行
So this is a bit of a preview, but I’m going to actually run this on the iPad.
我将选择 iPad 点击运行 它就会在 iPad 上运行了
So I just pick iPad, and hit Run, and it runs on the iPad.
我以后会为大多数 demo 这样做
And I’m going to start doing this for most of the demos,
在设备上运行 而不是在模拟器上
is running it on a device instead of running it in the simulator.
这更好一些 因为屏幕更大
It’s a little nicer because the screens a bit, little bigger
如这里所示 这是在我的 iPad 上
as you can see, and so here it is on my iPad here.
我可以轻击它 噢 死机了
And so I can tap and oop, it crashes.
这不是很好
Oh, well, that’s not good.
我做错了什么
What did I do wrong here?
我不知道哪里出了问题
Well, I don’t know what I did wrong, but I messed it
反正过程中我搞砸了 很抱歉
up when I preset this up so I’m sorry about that,
我会展示这个的
but I will show you that,
下周三开始 我将在设备上运行所有这些东西
I’ll start running all my demos hopefully on a device starting with next Wednesday’s thing
但愿到时候不会出现这样的错误 很抱歉
and hopefully I won’t make this mistake, sorry about that.
无论如何 今天就到这里
Anyway, okay, so that’s it.
还有问题吗
Any other questions about it?
更多内容 请访问我校官网 stanford.edu
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.